<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>CMandrill extension for Joomla!™ User's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

      <surname>Dimitrov</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>compojoom.com</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>27.04.2012</pubdate>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.3 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license is included in the appendix entitled "The GNU Free
      Documentation License".</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para>This book covers the use of the CMandrill extension &amp; plugin
      for Joomla. It does not cover any other extension available on
      compojoom.com .</para>
    </abstract>
  </bookinfo>

  <article>
    <para><revhistory>
        <revision>
          <revnumber>Revision 0.1</revnumber>

          <date>28.04.2012</date>

          <author>
            <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

            <surname>Dimitrov</surname>
          </author>
        </revision>

        <revision>
          <revnumber>Revision 0.2</revnumber>

          <date>21.01.2013</date>

          <author>
            <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

            <surname>Dimitrov</surname>
          </author>
        </revision>

        <revision>
          <revnumber>Revision 0.3</revnumber>

          <date>07.11.2013</date>

          <author>
            <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

            <surname>Dimitrov</surname>
          </author>
        </revision>
      </revhistory></para>
  </article>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>
      <title>Transactional emails</title>

      <para>Transactional emails are emails sent to an individual based on
      some action. It could be:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>an action they took directly</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>an action they were the target of</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>an inaction on their part (reminder to login into a
          website)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For example if a user registers on a website, most of the time he
      will get a confirmation or welcome mail. This is a transactional
      email.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Introducing Mandrillapp.com</title>

      <para>In April 2012 <ulink
      url="https://mailchimp.com/?pid=compojoom&amp;source=website">Mailchimp</ulink>
      introduced a new transactional email service called <ulink
      url="http://mandrill.com">Mandrill</ulink>. Mandrill is using the same
      optimized delivery engine that Mailchimp uses for the delivery of bulk
      newsletters – slightly modified for one-to-one email. The core features
      of Mandrill are:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Uses Mailchimp's awesome email delivery engine</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tracks opens and clicks</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Automatically adds Google Analytics tracking data to the
            URLs in the mail</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Has pretty, visual reports of the email results</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Allows you to tag the emails and see your stats filtered by
            tag</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Since the above description might not help you much, let us try
      with an example.</para>

      <para>Let us imagine that after registering on website X, we don't get
      the confirmation mail. What do we do? We contact the website owner and
      say - sorry, but we didn't receive the email. Let us imagine that we are
      the owner of website X - what do we do when a customer is telling us
      that he didn't receive the mail? We scratch our head and we say - look
      at your spam folder. But is the email really in the spam folder, was it
      actually sent? Is it still in the process of delivery or did it
      magically disappear from the face of the internet? In the past we did
      not have a simple way to know that, but now that has changed thanks to
      Mandrill. You can look at the emails being sent from your Joomla
      website, you can look at open/click rates and you can always know if a
      mail was delivered or it bounced back. This is what the Mandrill service
      is all about - giving you the peace of mind that your customers are
      receiving your emails &amp; the bonus of knowing if they actually open
      them and engage with the content.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Introducing CMandrill for Joomla</title>

      <para>Since you normally need to be a programmy nerd to use the service
      <ulink
      url="https://mailchimp.com/?pid=compojoom&amp;source=website">MailChimp</ulink>
      asked us to create an integration for Mandrill's API into Joomla. Back
      in April 2012 we came up with a simple plugin, that allowed you to just
      provide your API key and after that all e-mails* send by Joomla are
      going to be sent trough the Mandrill API. Since then we've used the
      plugin ourselves on compojoom.com and with each day we started to love
      the Mandrill service even more. That's why we decided that a plugin is
      great, but making a whole extension would allow us to even better
      integrate with the Mandrill API and make Joomla's emails just
      awesome!</para>

      <para>With the CMandrill extension you'll be able to:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Send emails through the Mandrill API optimised for
          speed</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Look at the most important stats (send, receive, bounce rates)
          directly from your Joomla backend</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Configure a global HTML template for emails</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Create HTML templates for specific components by specifying
          the class &amp; function names that send the mail</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>* All extensions that use the standard Joomla API for sending
      mails will continue to function as normal and the mails will be send
      trough Mandrill. If you are using extensions that have their own Mail
      classes, then those extensions will continue to function as normal, but
      they won't use the Mandrill API</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Installation and Updates</title>

    <para>Installing the Mandrill plugin for Joomla is easy it is not in any
    way different than installing any other Joomla!™ extension/module/plugin
    on your site. You can read the complete instructions for installing
    Joomla!™ extensions on the <ulink
    url="http://help.joomla.org/content/view/1476/235/">official Joomla help
    page</ulink> .Throughout this chapter we assume that you are familiar with
    these instructions and we will not duplicate them.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Getting the installation packages</title>

      <para>You can download the latest installation packages by visiting our
      site at <ulink
      url="https://compojoom.com">https://compojoom.com</ulink>. (you need to
      be login) In the download menu you will see the CMandrill menu item.
      Click on it. The latest releases are listed with the newest release
      always on top. Click on the release number and then download the ZIP
      package.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Compatibility</title>

        <para>The CMandrill extension for Joomla is currently compatible with
        Joomla 2.5 &amp; 3.0</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Updating to the latest version</title>

      <para>The plugin uses the standard update routine in Joomla. All you
      need to do is to go to Extensions -&gt; Extension Manager -&gt; Update
      in your Joomla backend. Then click on "Find Updates" if a new version of
      the plugin is available you will be able to update by selecting it and
      clicking on the "Update" button</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Using the CMandrill extension for Joomla</title>

    <para>The zip package of CMandrill will install both the extension and the
    plugin. After the installation you need to navigate to components -&gt;
    CMandrill and then access the options of the extension. Once you provide
    your Mandrill API key, you need to navigate to Extensions -&gt; Plugin
    manager and activate the "System - Mandrill" plugin.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Options</title>

      <para>To access the options screen navigate to Components -&gt;
      CMandrill and then click on the Options tag.</para>

      <para>In the basics tab you have the following parameters:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>API key - In the API key field provide your Mandrill API key
            (on the day of writing that documentation the API key could be
            found by clicking on the settings button (top right) at the
            mandrillapp.com page (you need to be logged in to see it))</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Use https - The use https option defines if the plugin
            should communicate with Mandrill server through an SSL connection
            or not. We recommend to set this option to yes if your hosting has
            the necessary PHP SSL libraries for this.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>In the Permissions tab you can specify which user group
      is allowed to access the backend of the extension.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Dashboard</title>

      <para>CMandrill's dashboard is showing your most important email
      delivery stats right in the backend of Joomla. On the dashboard you can
      see your sent, delivered data for the last 7 days or all time stats. You
      also have a list with the top 100 most clicked urls in your
      emails.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Templates</title>

      <para>In the templates view you'll be able to create a global HTML
      template that is going to be used when sending emails through Mandrill.
      Further more you can create templates just for specific extensions. For
      example you can have a global template that is used by all extensions,
      but for com_users you can have a customised template that gives newly
      registered users a coupon code along with their registration.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The HTML templates should be created directly in Mandrill. In
        CMandrill you just assign those templates to specific components,
        views or tasks.</para>
      </note>

      <section>
        <title>Creating a template</title>

        <para>On the template view click the new button. You'll be presented
        with a form that you need to fill out and save.</para>

        <para>Fields:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>title - enter a title for this HTML template. The title is
            only visible in the backend and is used to help you figure out
            what the template is actually for.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Status - the status of the template can be either publish or
            unpublished. Unpublished templates won't be used when sending
            emails</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Start publishing &amp; Finish Publishing - if you specify a
            timeframe here the template will be only used when the timeframe
            is met</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Mandrill Template - from this drop down field select the
            Mandrill template that this template is using.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Component - Use global if this template is meant to be used
            for the whole website. Use other if you are defining a template
            for a specific task</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Class name - the php class name that is sending the
            mail</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Function name - the php function in the class that is
            sending the mail</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <note>
          <para>You may be wondering - how do I find the class name and
          function name. Well if you are developer, you could always use the
          your favorite code editor and dig into the code. On the other hand
          there is a much easier way! Just trigger the task that you need a
          custom template for. Once you do, look at the activity tab in
          mandrill . You'll notice that the sent email has 2 tags -&gt; one
          starting with class_ and the other one starting with function_ .
          Those are your class name and function name. Just copy the part
          after the underscore and you are ready to go!</para>
        </note>

        <example>
          <title>Example - custom template for the Registration view</title>

          <para>1. On your site navigate to the registration view.</para>

          <para>2. Fill out all the details and click register. </para>

          <para>3. Login in mandrillapp.com and look at the activity tab. The
          mail that was sent about the registration has the following tags:
          class_UsersModelRegistration &amp; function_register</para>

          <para>4. Now go to CMandrill -&gt; templates -&gt; new. For
          component select other, for class name enter UsersModelRegistration
          and for function name enter register. Save the template</para>

          <para>5. That's it! Now the joomla registration emails will be sent
          using the template that you've specified!</para>
        </example>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>The Plugin</title>

    <para>When you install the CMandrill extension we also install the "System
    - Mandrill" plugin. This plugin is actually used to send the emails
    through the Mandrill API, so you'll need to enable it once you've provided
    your API key in the component's settings.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Once you enable the plugin, make sure that everything is working
      by executing an action on your site that sends an email. The email that
      you receive then should be coming from mandrill. (look at the sender's
      name)</para>
    </note>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>The CMandrill library</title>

    <para>Since version 3 the CMandrill component comes with a library called
    CMandrill. This library is a fork of the official <ulink
    url="https://bitbucket.org/mailchimp/mandrill-api-php">PHP Mandrill
    wrapper</ulink>. Our goal with this library is to make it compatible with
    the Joomla Coding standards and make it easy for developers to use it in
    their own projects based on the joomla framework, or in CLI scripts. If
    you are interested in the library, check out the <ulink
    url="https://github.com/compojoom/lib_cmandrill">github
    repository</ulink>!</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Good to know</title>

    <section>
      <title>Sending limits</title>

      <para>Depending on your Mandrill account there are different sending
      limits that apply for you. If you are a free user then this limit is
      currently 12 000 emails per month. For more information on sending
      limits please refer to <ulink
      url="http://help.mandrill.com/customer/portal/articles/464936-mailchimp-bundled-pricing">Mandrill's
      help pages</ulink>.</para>

      <para>The current implementation of the plugin checks how many emails
      you have send for the day and how big your sending limit is. If you have
      reached your sending e-mail then the plugin will fall back to the
      standard JMailer class and will send the mails according to the settings
      that you have specified in your Global Configuration (Joomla's global
      configuration. Accessible through Site -&gt; Global Configuration -&gt;
      Server -&gt; Mail Settings)</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>CC emails</title>

      <para>If a Joomla extension tries to send an email that has the CC
      option set, then the plugin will fall back to the standard JMailer class
      and won't use the Mandrill API.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>What happens with rejected mails?</title>

      <para>In some situations the Mandrill API won't send the mail and will
      return a rejected status for it. In this case the plugin will try to
      send the mail to the recipient again, but this time using the standard
      JMailer class.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Logging</title>

      <para>The plugin uses the standard Joomla JLog class to log errors and
      warnings. The logs are saved in the folder configured in your Joomla's
      Global Configuration. The logs are split by Month. You can expect them
      to identify situations in which the plugin was not able to send the
      email using Mandrill's API and has fallen back to the standard JMailer
      class.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Events logged</title>

        <para>The plugin logs following events:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use of CC option for sending emails</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Daily sending quota exceeded</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Queued messages</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Rejected messages</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Unsupported attachments</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tags</title>

      <para>For each Mail we try to add the following tags:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>option - identifies the Joomla component sending the
          email</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>view - identifies the view of the component sending the
          mail</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>task - identifies the task that is executed by the component
          sending the mail</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Each of this tags is added only if we are able to identify
      it.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Attachments</title>

      <para>Currently the Mandrill API supports only attachments with the mime
      type image/*, text/* and application/pdf. If your Joomla site is sending
      emails that contain other attachments, then the plugin will recognise
      this and will fall back to the standard JMailer class.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Email HTML templates</title>

      <para>You can have only 1 global template, but you can have as many
      custom HTML templates as you wish.</para>

      <section>
        <title>How do we determine which template to use?</title>

        <para>When we are sending the mail we are trying to find out if you
        have a template that matches all criteria - class name and function
        name. If we find such a template we are going to use it. If we don't,
        then we will use the global template - if one is provided. If you
        don't have a global template, then we will send the mail as plain
        text.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>What modifications are made to the content of HTML
        mails</title>

        <para>If we determine that we need to use an HTML template, then we
        need to slightly modify the content of the mail. Most mails in Joomla
        are sent as plain-text. But if you are using an HTML template you want
        this plain text to be properly formatted. So that is why when we need
        to send an HTML template and we find out that the text is in
        plain-text we parse it and add &lt;br /&gt; where necessary &amp; we
        also change HTML links to &lt;a href="html link"&gt;html
        link&lt;/a&gt; . Those small modifications make sure that the mail
        will look fine in the user's inbox.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Where do we put the content of the Joomla email in the HTML
        template?</title>

        <para>Your HTML template should contain the following code:</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;div mc:edit="main_content"&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>This is where the content of the Joomla mail is going to be
        inserted.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Support</title>

    <para>The CMandrill extension for Joomla is released free of charge.
    Community support is available in our Forum in the CMandrill
    section.</para>
  </chapter>
</book>
